A Guide to the Catoctin Mountain Alliance, 1985-1995
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Catoctin Mountain Alliance 1985-1995
Thomas Balch Library
M 031
1.66 cu. ft.
These records date from 1985 after the filing of the first request for a special exception by Beacon Hills Farm Associates and continue until 1995 with the announcement that marketing would begin on the Beacon Hill property under the plan of development which had been approved by the Loudoun County Planning Commission in 1992, a proposal approved by the Catoctin Mountain Alliance.
B. Powell Harrison
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection open for research.
Acquisition Information
Sharon Kearns, Leesburg VA
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2006.0024
Historical Information
On 27 June 1979 Beacon Hill, an estate composed of approximately 2,083 acres owned by Arthur (1903-1983) and Mary (1913-1997) Godfrey, was sold to Saudi Prince Talal bin Abdul Aziz (1935-) for just over five million dollars. Godfrey was a nationally known radio personality in the 1950's who sometimes broadcast from his farm. The prince made extensive changes and additions to the property, spending approximately 18 million dollars on these projects
On 16 November 1985 Beacon Hill was bought by a partnership called Beacon Hill Farm Associates (BHFA), later changed to Beacon Hill Farm Associates II, Limited Partnership. In September 1985, based on a conditional contract for the property BHFA applied to the Board of Zoning Appeals for a special exception to begin development of this property. This action began a ten year long process of filings for various levels of development. Neighbors of Beacon Hill organized Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association which closely monitored each step and fought the plans before the Loudoun County Planning Commission, with the Planning and Zoning Departments of the County, and in court. B. Powell Harrison (25 Aug 1911-1 Nov 2000), was president of this association, and lawsuits were filed by him and his wife, Agnes Harrison. The name of the organization changed to Catoctin Mountain Alliance in 1987, but the focus remained the same: to fight the high density development of the targeted property. During the course of this fight Loudoun County Board of Supervisors passed the Mountainside Development Overlay District to regulate development on the mountainsides in Loudoun County; this law covered the Beacon Hill property.
The struggle between Beacon Hill Farm Associates II, Limited Partnership and Catoctin Mountain Alliance continued until 1992 when Loudoun County government approved plans to allow houses to be built on large tracts, an option which met with approval of Catoctin Mountain Alliance.
Scope and Content
These papers are files compiled by B. Powell Harrison who chaired this organization, originally named the Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association; in February 1987 the name was briefly changed to TBD Group (To Be Determined); on 1 June 1987 the group voted to change its name to Catoctin Mountain Alliance. These records date from 1985 after the filing of the first request for a special exception by Beacon Hills Farm Associates and continue until 1995 with the announcement that marketing would begin on the Beacon Hill property under the plan of development which had been approved by the Loudoun County Planning Commission in 1992, a proposal approved by the Catoctin Mountain Alliance. Records include news articles, speeches, letters, memos, zoning applications, lawsuits, financial records, and Harrison's notes regarding the proposed development of Beacon Hill. Records reflect order in which documents were arranged in Harrison's files; they are not always in chronological order.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Other Finding Aid
None
Technical Requirements
None
Related Material
Vertical File, "Arthur Godfrey," Thomas Balch Library; Lewis Edwards Architectural Survey, "Beacon Hill," Thomas Balch Library
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous letters, news articles, and applications, 1986-1987
  - Letters, news articles, petitions, and notices to the members of Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association, July 1979-November 1985
  - Letters and public statements, January 1986-May 1986
  - Letters, memos, and news articles, February-April 1986
  - Financial records of Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association, 1985-1986
  - Memos, letters, and reports, July 1986-June 1987
  - Membership list of Beacon Hill Neighborhood Association, letters, and memos, November 1985-March 1987
  - Letters and memos, November 1985-May 1987
  - News articles, press releases, memos, and advertisements, May-June 1987
  - Public statements, memos, and letters, September-December 1987
  - Statements, Letters, and memos, August-87
  - Statements, news articles, and letters, January-March 1988
- (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous articles, letters, presentations most of which concern lawsuits regarding Beacon Hill, January-June 1988
  - Miscellaneous articles, letters, presentations most of which concern lawsuits regarding Beacon Hill, July-December 1988
  - Miscellaneous articles, letters, reports, opinions, and presentations regarding "Episode 6" in which Beacon Hill Farm Associates II Limited Partnership sought to reverse the decision of the zoning administrator which said that the Mountainside Overlay District Ordinance applied to the their subdivision applications
  - Miscellaneous articles, letters, presentations regarding Beacon Hill. Also in opposition to Village Ordinance being considered as part of new Comprehensive) Plan, January 1989-October 1991
  - Miscellaneous papers from 1989 mainly regarding Beacon Hill Farm Associates II's refiling of lawsuits, 18-May-89
  - Papers concerning lawsuits of Beacon Hill Farm Associates II and their applications to amend Rural Land Management Plan and application for subdivision of part of Beacon Hill Farm, January-April 1990
  - Letters, articles, presentation regarding Beacon Hill Farm Associates II's application for special exception to allow subdivision of 1,092 acres of Beacon Hill into 70 building lots. Articles and reports relating Catoctin Mountain Associates' dropping its opposition to this proposal on conditions affecting road systems and mountain views. Letters and article reporting plans by Elm Street Development of McLean to begin marketing the approved lots. 1992-1995
- (Box 3)
  - Letters requesting donations to support work of Catoctin Mountain Alliance, thank you letters to donors, October 1988-September 1990
  - Thank you letters to donors to Catoctin Mountain Alliance, 1990-1992
  - Catoctin Mountain Alliance members and donation information, 1987
  - Miscellaneous correspondence regarding Catoctin Mountain Alliance, 1987
  - Thank you letters to donors, 1988
  - Information regarding Loudoun County's Mountainside Overlay Ordinance
  - Legal study commissioned by Piedmont Environmental Council and Catoctin Mountain Alliance of "Comprehensive Plan and its relation to the zoning ordinance" prepared by attorneys Robert E. Sevila and Tersh Boasberg; press releases; miscellaneous financial information
  - Letters, memos, reports; finances of Catoctin Mountain Alliance, June 1987-December 1989
  - Bills, letters, financial records of Catoctin Mountain Alliance, 1990-1995
- (Box 4)
  - Studies, letters, memos from Connie Krueger, Secretary of Catoctin Mountain Alliance (CMA), to B. Powell Harrison, President of CMA, 1989-1990
  - Studies, memos, public statements regarding development proposed by Beacon Hill Associates II; news articles regarding plans for other developments, 1987-1989
  - Updated Beacon Hill Residential Development Traffic Impact Study prepared by Kellerco
  - Studies and reports of Virginia Department of Transportation and Loudoun County agencies regarding proposed development of Beacon Hill. Statement of B. Powell Harrison to Board of Supervisors, 14-Dec-89
  - Statements, memos, reports regarding development of Beacon Hill; outline for Loudoun County, Virginia Zoning Ordinance, 1989-1990
  - Memos, reports letters, news articles, 1988-1990
- (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous reports, articles, memos, lawsuits regarding development of Beacon Hill Estate. Chapter 36, Code of Virginia. 1987-1988
  - Beacon Hill Project Schedule, 1987 Cumulative Supplement, Code of Virginia, reports, lawsuits, memos regarding proposed Beacon Hill development, 1987
  - Reports, memos, lawsuits, zoning applications, magazine article, 1987-1988
  - Zoning application, memos, articles, Beacon Hill Site Access Plan prepared by Kellerco, 17-Jul-87
  - Letters, memos, zoning application, news articles regarding development of Beacon Hill Estate; plan for development of Cheswick in western Loudoun.